<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<component>
	<id>1</id>
	<literal>NATURAL FOREST AREAS</literal>
	<subsystem>2</subsystem>
	<description>Natural forest areas are the direct result of conservation efforts and, in some cases, of 25-year-old (or older) reforestations planted by the farmers’ parents and grandparents. </description>
	<img>monte.jpg</img>
</component>
<component>
	<id>2</id>
	<literal>REFORESTED AREAS</literal>
	<subsystem>2</subsystem>
	<description>Each farmer assigns, on average, 13 hectares of his land to reforestation. Most of these lands are hillsides and slopes where agriculture has ceased because of excessive soil erosion and nutrient depletion. Reforestations are 1 to 15 years old and subsidized by federal and state programs. In general, the establishment and maintenance of these areas employ family labor. </description>
	<img>reforestacion.jpg</img>
</component>
<component>
	<id>3</id>
	<literal>POULTRY</literal>
	<subsystem>3</subsystem>
	<description>Turkeys, chickens, and geese are commonly raised in the family backyard. Birds are fed throughout the year with grain from the agricultural plot. They constitute an important source of meat and eggs. </description>
	<img>aves.jpg</img>
</component>
<component>
	<id>4</id>
	<literal>CULTIVATED PLOTS</literal>
	<subsystem>1</subsystem>
	<description> A variety of crops are raised during the 9-month agricultural cycle. Landrance maize is the main crop. Some farmers cultivate native varieties small of squash (Cucurbita pepo L.), fig-leaved gourd (Cucurbita ficifolia), and beans (Phaseolus vulgaris L.) on small areas of the plot. </description>
	<img>cultivo.jpg</img>
</component>
<component>
	<id>5</id>
	<literal>FALLOW PLOTS</literal>
	<subsystem>1</subsystem>
	<description>The fallow period lasts 11 months. After harvesting, cattle are introduced into the plot to feed on crop residues and non-target plants that grow during the rainy season. </description>
	<img>descanso.jpg</img>
</component>
<component>
	<id>6</id>
	<literal>SOIL</literal>
	<subsystem>1</subsystem>
	<description>Agricultural soils are volcanic Andosols with low availability of nitrogen and phosphorous. Nutrient inputs are mainly organic fertilizer provided in-situ (by livestock) and applied pig manure.</description>
	<img>suelo.jpg</img>
</component>
<component>
	<id>7</id>
	<literal>CATTLE</literal>
	<subsystem>3</subsystem>
	<description>Cattle provide dairy products, beef, and animal power for agricultural labors and transportation of products. They also function as a sort of savings account; in case of need, animals are sold to regional slaughterhouses. A head of cattle is ready for sale after a 3-year fattening period. </description>
	<img>ganado.jpg</img>
</component>
<component>
	<id>8</id>
	<literal>HORSES</literal>
	<subsystem>3</subsystem>
	<description>Horses are an important source of animal power. These animals are used in agricultural labors and to transport firewood and wooden posts.</description>
	<img>caballos.jpg</img>
</component>
<component>
	<id>9</id>
	<literal>FAMILY</literal>
	<subsystem>4</subsystem>
	<description>An average family has 6 members. The family structure responds to a strong patriarchy, which is strengthened as the land-owning rights are traditionally assigned exclusively to the head of the family (usually the father). Nonetheless, in recent years, migration has slowly changed family organization. These changes include (1) the transfer of productive land tenure rights, responsibilities, and knowledge to women; (2) reduced availability of family labor; and (3) an increase in the average age of active producers. </description>
	<img>familia.jpg</img>
</component>
<component>
	<id>10</id>
	<literal>FAMILY ASSETS </literal>
	<subsystem>4</subsystem>
	<description> The family has a variety of productive and non-productive assets related to the management of their land, such as accumulated knowledge and means of production.</description>
	<img>acervos.jpg</img>
</component>
