<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<flow>
	<id>1</id>
	<literal>TIMBER</literal>
	<description>Timber is extracted on a small scale for fence construction, handicrafts and furniture making. </description>
	<subsysExit>2</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>4</subsysEntry>
	<img>madera.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>2</id>
	<literal>FORESTRY GRANTS</literal>
	<description>Government subsidies comprise state economic support and plants to establish reforestations. In addition, the federal government issues an annual payment for maintenance of forest plantations. </description>
	<subsysExit>5</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>2</subsysEntry>
	<img>dinero_pino.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>3</id>
	<literal>NON-TIMBER PRODUCTS</literal>
	<description>Other products extracted from forests are pine seeds (which are sold to regional nurseries), pine cones and needles (used in handicraft making), medicinal plants (such as “pescadillo”, “tepuza”, “cilantrillo”, etc.), and editable plants and fungi (“quelites”, berries, “tejocote”, and mushrooms). </description>
	<subsysExit>2</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>4</subsysEntry>
	<img>otros_forestal.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>4</id>
	<literal>FIREWOOD</literal>
	<description>Firewood is a product that mainly satisfies the family energy needs. Most firewood is obtained by gathering dead oak branches and trunks.</description>
	<subsysExit>2</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>4</subsysEntry>
	<img>lenya_carbon.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>5</id>
	<literal>FORESTRY LABOR</literal>
	<description>Farmers generally visit forest plantations daily for vigilance and maintenance.</description>
	<subsysExit>4</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>2</subsysEntry>
	<img>mano_forestal.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>6</id>
	<literal>MEAT AND DAIRY PRODUCTS</literal>
	<description>The products obtained from this subsystem are dairy products, meat, and eggs. Most is used for home comsumption. </description>
	<subsysExit>3</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>4</subsysEntry>
	<img>pollo_queso.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>7</id>
	<literal>MONETARY INCOME</literal>
	<description>The main source of income for agroforestry system families is the sale of wood, meat, dairy products, and surpluses from crop production. Another important source of income is the remittances from family members working in large cities within the country or abroad. </description>
	<subsysExit>5</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>4</subsysEntry>
	<img>dinero.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>8</id>
	<literal>FERTILIZER</literal>
	<description>Cattle grazing in the forested areas provide nutrients for growing trees. </description>
	<subsysExit>3</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>2</subsysEntry>
	<img>estiercol.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>9</id>
	<literal>ANIMAL HUSBANDRY</literal>
	<description>The family provides all labor invested in the livestock subsystem. Labors include milking and herding the animals. </description>
	<subsysExit>4</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>3</subsysEntry>
	<img>mano_pecuario.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>10</id>
	<literal>PURCHASE OF FORAGE</literal>
	<description>Most forage consumed by cattle is obtained from the agroforestry production unit. However, some forage is bought in local markets to make up for shortages during the dry season. </description>
	<subsysExit>5</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>3</subsysEntry>
	<img>foraje_externa.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>11</id>
	<literal>FORAGE AND NON-TARGET PLANTS</literal>
	<description>On average, farm plots produce almost four tons of forage per hectare a year. However, only half is of high quality. Some producers also cultivate forage (mainly oats) on small portions of land as a feeding supplement. This reduces the fattening period. </description>
	<subsysExit>1</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>3</subsysEntry>
	<img>foraje_agricola.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>12</id>
	<literal>ANIMAL POWER</literal>
	<description>Tillage is performed using oxen for plowing and planting, and horses for covering seed during sowing and for cultivating.</description>
	<subsysExit>3</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>1</subsysEntry>
	<img>traccion.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>13</id>
	<literal>FERTILIZERS</literal>
	<description>Producers base fertilization mainly on application of one ton of pig or cow manure per hectare. Manure is bought from farms in the region.</description>
	<subsysExit>5</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>1</subsysEntry>
	<img>fertilizantes.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>14</id>
	<literal>AGRICULTURAL GRANTS</literal>
	<description>Subsidies are channeled through a federal government program (PROCAMPO) and consists of $1,300 pesos per hectare of cultivated land ($100 USD/ha).</description>
	<subsysExit>5</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>1</subsysEntry>
	<img>dinero.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>15</id>
	<literal>AGRICULTURAL PRACTICES</literal>
	<description> In agricultural production, work is divided into pre-harvest activities (related to tillage, planting, and weed control), and harvesting. The family provides most of the labor required throughout the agricultural cycle.</description>
	<subsysExit>4</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>1</subsysEntry>
	<img>mano_agricola.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>16</id>
	<literal>MAIZE</literal>
	<description>Maize obtained from the agricultural subsystem is used for home consumption. Production on agricultural plots located on slopes is very low. Therefore, surpluses for commercialization are also very small. </description>
	<subsysExit>1</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>4</subsysEntry>
	<img>exced_maiz.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>17</id>
	<literal>OTHER AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTS</literal>
	<description>Other products from the agricultural subsystem are squash and fig-leaf gourd, which are basically used for household consumption.</description>
	<subsysExit>1</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>4</subsysEntry>
	<img>otrosProdAgric.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>18</id>
	<literal>MAIZE</literal>
	<description>Sometimes, a surplus is obtained from agricultural production and is sold in the local market or exchanged for seeds of different varieties. However, the easiest way to sell the maize surplus in processed form as “tortillas”, “tamales”, “corundas”, “atole”, among others.</description>
	<subsysExit>1</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>5</subsysEntry>
	<img>granos_maiz.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>19</id>
	<literal>RAW WOOD</literal>
	<description>The ejido has an official forestry management plan that allows the extraction and commercialization of wood in regional sawmills.</description>
	<subsysExit>2</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>5</subsysEntry>
	<img>madera_rollo.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>20</id>
	<literal>MANURE</literal>
	<description>From January through March, cattle feed on the non-target plants and crop residues left standing on fallow plots after the harvest of maize and leave manure on the plot to nourish soil for the next agricultural cycle. </description>
	<subsysExit>3</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>1</subsysEntry>
	<img>estiercol.jpg</img>
</flow>
<flow>
	<id>21</id>
	<literal>LIVESTOCK PRODUCTS</literal>
	<description>Meat and dairy products are the main animal subsystem products sold in markets.</description>
	<subsysExit>3</subsysExit>
	<subsysEntry>5</subsysEntry>
	<img>carne_queso.jpg</img>
</flow>


