<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<!-- initialization -->
<msg key="init.loadData">LOADING DATA...</msg>
<msg key="init.title">MESMIS: STEP BY STEP</msg>
<msg key="init.description">Interactive example of a sustainability evaluation using the MESMIS framework </msg>
<msg key="init.authors1">Yankuic Galvan, Max Pimm, Tamara Ortiz</msg>
<msg key="init.authors2">Marta Astier, Omar Masera</msg>
<msg key="init.initializeGlobals">SEARCHING GLOBAL VARIABLES…</msg>
<msg key="init.initializeActivities">STARTING EXERCISES...</msg>
<msg key="init.skipIntro">Skip Intro ></msg>
<msg key="init.support">Project made possible with financial and logistical support of:</msg>
<msg key="init.support.1"> Research Center in Agriculture Sciences (CICA-UAEM), Mexico</msg>
<msg key="init.support.2">Center of Ecosystems Research (CIEco-UNAM), Mexico</msg>
<msg key="init.support.3">National Council on Science and Technology (CONACYT), Mexico</msg>
<msg key="init.support.4"> Southern Border College (ECOSUR), Mexico</msg>
<msg key="init.support.5">Interdisciplinary Group of Appropriate Rural Technology (GIRA A.C), Mexico</msg>
<msg key="init.support.6">National Ministry of Environment and Natural Resources (SEMARNAT), Mexico</msg>

<!-- principal menu -->
<msg key="menuPrin.btn1.txt">STEP 1</msg>
<msg key="menuPrin.btn1a.txt">STEP 1</msg>
<msg key="menuPrin.btn2.txt">STEP 2</msg>
<msg key="menuPrin.btn3.txt">STEP 3</msg>
<msg key="menuPrin.btn4.txt">STEP 4</msg>
<msg key="menuPrin.btn5.txt">STEP 5</msg>
<msg key="menuPrin.btn6.txt">STEP 6</msg>
<msg key="menuPrin.title">MESMIS:$nSTEP BY STEP</msg>
<msg key="menuPrin.welcome">WELCOME</msg>
<msg key="menuPrin.preface.title">PRESENTATION</msg>
<msg key="menuPrin.preface.txt">This module illustrates the application of the MESMIS framework through a simple and interactive example. The case under study is an adaptation from the work published by Astier et al. (2004) with additional information from Ortiz (2005).  $n$nThe purpose of this material is not to analyze every single aspect involved in a sustainability evaluation, but to overview MESMIS’ most elementary methodological aspects and to present its different stages in a logical sequence. The first step in the framework is the characterization of the system: defining, describing, and understanding the unit of analysis. Once this process is completed, it is possible to identify the critical aspects that affect or strengthen its sustainability. These critical aspects will be the reference for the selection of sustainability indicators. Finally, it is necessary to integrate the results and define strategies for improving the management systems under study. $n$nThe case study is an “año y vez” agricultural system (a system in which land is cultivated one year and the next is left to fallow) practiced by peasants in the communities of the Patzcuaro Lake basin in Michoacan, a rainfed agricultural zone typical of the mountainous regions of Mexico. This kind of agriculture is employed on small plots, sloping lands, and low quality soils. $n$nThe example compares the sustainability of an agricultural system managed with conventional practices and the same system after five years of incorporating soil conservation practices and introducing new crops to diversify agricultural production. The objective is to identify the comparative advantages of each system and define elements that can be used to develop strategies to improve the “año y vez” systems in the region.$n$nThis material is specially intended for technicians, peasant promoters, and students interested in putting into practice sustainability evaluations of peasant natural resource management systems. </msg>

<msg key="menuPrin.credits.title">Credits and Acknowledgements</msg>
<msg key="menuPrin.credits.txt">Texts: Yankuic Galvan, Tamara Ortiz, Marta Astier y Omar Masera$n$nDesign: Yankuic Galvan abd Max Pimm$n$nProgramming: Max Pimm$n$nWe would like to thank Luis Garcia Barrios and Carlos Gonzalez for their valuable ideas and comments, which helped us design and improve this work. We also want to thank Andres Camu for the images that helped illustrate this material. To Mara Benez, Claudia Mosqueda, Lucio P. Fernandez, Abraham Ocampo, Jose Hernandez, Helda Morales, Jose Nahed and Lorena Soto, we remain thankful for their valuable suggestions during the earlier stages of development of this material. We also appreciate the comments from the master students at the Universidad Internacional de Andalucia’s master’s program in in Agroecology and Sustainable Rural Development in Latin America and Spain (2006). Finally, we want to thank SEMARNAT and CONACYT for funding this material through project SEMARNAT-2002-C01-0800.</msg>

<!-- step 1: Definition of the production system-->
<msg key="defineSystem.intro.text">This section explains how to characterize a natural resource management system at the scale of the production unit and farm plot. $n$nThe example illustrates a characterization through flowcharts for a typical production unit and for the agricultural subsystem practiced in Casas Blancas. $n$n In this first step of the evaluation, the main characteristics of the reference agricultural system are identified and compared to an alternative agricultural system integrating agroecological practices.</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.intro.title">STEP 1: CHARACTERIZING NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT SYSTEMS</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.localization.title">LOCATION OF THE AREA OF STUDY</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.localization.text">Casas Blancas is an “ejido” located on the municipality of Salvador Escalante, which is part of the Purhépecha region of the Patzcuaro Lake basin in Michoacan, Mexico. $n$nThe ejido, just like many other communities situated over the Trans-Mexican Volcanic Belt, has an irregular landscape of hills and volcanoes. $n$nSoils are of volcanic origin, mostly Andosols with low availability of phosphorus and nitrogen. $n$nClimate is temperate and the dominant vegetation are pine and oak forests.</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.localization2.title">SOCIOECONOMIC CHARACTERISTICS</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.localization2.text">Casas Blancas is a small community of around 1,000 people and 1,751 hectares of land. The main economic activities are agriculture, forestry, animal husbandry, and, to a lesser extent, handcrafts. The strategies of production and family organization depend heavily upon these activities, and it is the family that provides most of the labor. $n$nLand tenure is a form of communal usufruct called “ejido”. The ejido Casas Blancas is conformed of 54 farmers, each one having a 30 hectare plot of land. The decision-making institution is the ejido assembly. The assembly makes decisions on management of communal areas, collective community work, and agrarian disputes.</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.productionUnit.title">THE PRODUCTION UNIT (PU)</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.productionUnit.text"> The PU has 30 hectares of land which is used for agriculture, forestry, and animal husbandry to provide goods for family consumption, and the surplus is sold. The family does the planning, makes decisions on management and destination of the production, and provides for most of the necessary labor. $n$nTo characterize the PU, it is necessary to identify: $n$n- The subsystems$n$n- The components, which comprise all the elements that make up the system$n$n- The flows, which indicate relationships (within the PU and those of the PU with the outside) among subsystems and components. Flows also confer functionality to the system as a whole.</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.productionUnit.instruction">Now, you will learn, step by step, how to characterize a typical production unit or agroforestry system. </msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.excercise.intro">To characterize the UP, we will build an input-output flowchart, which will allow us to articulate the different elements conforming the PU. Click “Add Subsystems” to start. </msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.excercise.addComponents">Now, you will identify the components for each subsystem in the PU. To continue, click “Add Components”. </msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.excercise.addRestOfComponents">Before you continue, please add the missing components</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.excercise.addFlows">Now, identify the different flows within and to the exterior of the PU. To continue, click "Add Flows".</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.excercise.addRestOfFlows">Before you continue, please add the missing flows</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.excercise.complete">You have finished building the flowchart for the PU. We will now focus on characterizing the agricultural subsystem. Click “Next” to continue. </msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.evaluationObject.title">Object of Evaluation</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.evaluationObject.text">The previous example showed a very general characterization of the PU. Following the same logic displayed on the flowcharts, we will take a closer look at the characteristics of the agricultural system that is our object of evaluation. This system, which from now on we will call the Reference Agricultural System (RAS), will be compared to an Alternative Agricultural System (AAS) that integrates agroecological practices. </msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.systemCasasBlancas.familyUnit">FAMILY UNIT</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.systemCasasBlancas.exterior">EXTERIOR</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.systemCasasBlancas.exteriorElmnts">Market,$nGovernment,$nCulture,$nEcosystem.</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.systemCasasBlancas.work">Work</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.systemCasasBlancas.corn">Maize</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.systemCasasBlancas.subsid">Subsidies, Seeds,$nManure and Fertilizer</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.systemCasasBlancas.cultivatedField">CULTIVATED PLOTS</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.systemCasasBlancas.restingField">FALLOW PLOTS</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.systemCasasBlancas.nutrients1">Nutrients</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.systemCasasBlancas.nutrients2">Nutrients$n(in situ fertilizing)</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.systemCasasBlancas.cattle">LIVESTOCK</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.systemCasasBlancas.soil">SOIL</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.SARSystem.title">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE REFERENCE AGRICULTURAL SYSTEM</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.SARSystem1.text">Agriculture in Casas Blancas follows the “año y vez” system. Land is cultivated for a year and then left fallow for the next agricultural cycle. Livestock is regularly introduced on fallow plots under this system. Producers assign 6 ha for agricultural production. They divide this area into two 3 ha plots, rotating cultivation yearly. Each plot is cultivated for 9 months (March-November) and then left fallow for 11 months (December-October). </msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.SARSystem2.text">The objective of production is self-sufficiency and sale of surplus. </msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.SARSystem3.text"> The main crop is maize. The kinds used are native landrace white, yellow, and black varieties. Also small areas are cultivated with squash and figleaf gourd.</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.SARSystem4.text">Pig manure and chemical fertilizers are used to fertilize the soil. There are also nutrient contributions from livestock during the fallow period.</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.SARSystem5.text">Tillage and other cultural tasks are animal-powered.</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.SARSystem6.text">The family provides most of the labor needed to maintain the system.</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.SARSystem7.text">No soil conservation practices are applied.</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.AltSystem.title">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE ALTERNATIVE AGRICULTURAL SYSTEM</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.AltSystem1.text"> The alternative agricultural system keeps most of the characteristics of the RAS, but substitutes chemical fertilizing by planting maize in association with legumes and integrating soil conservation practices.</msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.AltSystem2.text">It incorporates intercropping maize, beans and peas. </msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.AltSystem3.text">The use of organic fertilizers is increased during the planting period. </msg>
<msg key="defineSystem.AltSystem4.text">Finally, the RAS implements soil conservation practices consisting in leaving a greater portion of crop residues as mulch.</msg>

<!-- Component selector -->
<msg key="selectComponents.title">Select Components</msg>
<msg key="selectComponents.intro">Select a component, read its description, and identify the subsystem to which it belongs. Click “Add” to insert the component into the flowchart or “Add all” to insert all components automatically. </msg>
<msg key="selectComponents.selectSubsystem">Select the subsystem for this component</msg>
<msg key="selectComponents.detailpane.title">Component Details</msg>
<msg key="selectComponents.error.noCompSelected">Please select a component to add </msg>
<msg key="selectComponents.error.noSubsysSelected">Please select the subsystem for the component"{0}"</msg>
<msg key="selectComponents.error.wrongSubsystem">The component "{0}" does not belong to the subsystem "{1}"</msg>

<!-- Flow selector -->
<msg key="selectFlows.title">Select Flows</msg>
<msg key="selectFlows.intro">Select a flow to read its description and identify the direction of the flow between subsystems. Click “Add” to insert the flow into the diagram, or “Add all” to insert all flows automatically. </msg>
<msg key="selectFlows.detailpane.title">Flow Details</msg>
<msg key="selectFlows.selectSubsysExit">Select the source subsystem</msg>
<msg key="selectFlows.selectSubsysEntry">Select the recipient subsystem</msg>
<msg key="selectFlows.error.noFlowSelected">Please select a flow to add </msg>
<msg key="selectFlows.error.noSubsysExitSelected">Please select the source subsystem for flow "{0}"</msg>
<msg key="selectFlows.error.noSubsysEntrySelected">Please select the recipient subsystem for flow "{0}"</msg>
<msg key="selectFlows.error.wrongSubsystems">The flow "{0}" does not go from "{1}" to "{2}"</msg>

<!-- Step 2: Strengths and weaknesnes -->
<msg key="strengthsAndWeaknesses.intro.title">STEP 2: IDENTIFYING STRENGTHS AND WEAKNESSES</msg>
<msg key="strengthsAndWeaknesses.intro.text"> Strengths and weaknesses (S&W) refers to the aspects that (positively or negatively) affect the sustainability of natural resource management systems. Using the diagnostic criteria as a guide, it is possible to ask what kind of problems in terms of returns, efficiency, conservation, diversity, etc., the system faces, and what aspects strengthen the system. $n$nWe will now examine the aspects that strengthen and weaken the sustainability of the RAS.  With this information, we will be able to identify the indicators that are most relevant for evaluating the RAS, as well as its advantages or disadvantages over the AAS.</msg>

<msg key="strengthsAndWeaknesses.component.title"> S&W OF THE REFERENCE AGRICULTURAL SYSTEM</msg>

<!-- Step 3 & 4: Select Indicators -->
<msg key="selectIndicators.intro.title">STEP 3 AND 4: DERIVING AND MEASURING SUSTAINABILITY INDICATORS</msg>
<msg key="selectIndicators.intro.text"> Once we have characterized the systems under evaluation and identified its main problems and strengths, we can derive the corresponding indicators. Through these indicators, we will be able to detect changes over time in terms of the system’s sustainability. $n$nWe will now select indicators for the RAS’s S&W identified in the previous section. We will then articulate the attributes and diagnostic criteria with the S&W and the indicators.</msg>
<msg key="selectIndicators.comp.atributesTitle">Attributes</msg>
<msg key="selectIndicators.comp.atributes">Productivity$nStability$nEquity$nAdaptability$nSelf-reliance (Self-empowerment)</msg>
<msg key="selectIndicators.comp.presentCriteria"> The sustainability attributes allow the evaluator to focus on the systemic aspects that are most relevant for the adequate functioning of the system. The diagnostic criteria translate these systemic properties into more concrete elements and constitute a basis to derive the indicators.$n$n(Use the scroll bar to move the screen) </msg>
<msg key="selectIndicators.comp.presentStrenthsAndWeakenesses">With the S&W, we can identify the critical aspects that positively or negatively affect the systemic properties of management systems. </msg>
<msg key="selectIndicators.comp.presentIndicators">Finally, we translate the S&W into an indicator or group of indicators through which we can monitor changes in the system through time.</msg>
<msg key="selectIndicators.comp.pressIndicators">Click the corresponding indicator to read its description.</msg>

<!-- Step 5: Integration of results and evaluation -->
<msg key="defineAmoebas.intro.title">STEP 5: INTEGRATING RESULTS</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.intro.text">This stage of the evaluation cycle moves us from a phase of differentiation to one of synthesis. The integration of indicators will allow us to visualize the comparative advantages of each management system (RAS and AAS) over each indicator, and it will help develop a value judgment about their sustainability. To integrate indicators adequately we need to:$n$n- Synthesize indicators into a single matrix of results$n- Determine reference values and standardize indicators$n- Represent indicators graphically$n -Identify (if possible) synergic and competing relations among indicators.</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.resultsSnthesis.title">SYNTHESIS OF RESULTS</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.standardization.title">DETERMINING THE LEVEL OF PERFORMANCE</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.tblIndic.intro1">A first step towards the integration of results is the synthesis of the data obtained on each indicator into a single matrix that specifies:</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.tblIndic.intro2">The indicators used and their units of measurement.</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.tblIndic.intro3">The direction of change desired for the indicator; that is, to define if more is better (to maximize) or worse (to minimize). </msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.tblIndic.intro4">The values for the indicators on each of the evaluated systems. </msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.tblIndic.intro5">Once we have looked at our indicators and its values, we can proceed to estimate the level of performance. To this end, we will use a maximum-and-minimum interval. </msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.tblIndic.intro6">The minimum value represents the worst scenario for the indicator, while the maximum value represents the ideal scenario (when the objective is to minimize, the minimum and maximum are interpreted the other way around).</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.tblIndic.intro7">Using the reference values we can determine the level of performance by applying the following formula:$n$nNS=(V-Vmin/Vmax-Vmin)*100 o$n$nNS=(Vmax-V/Vmax-Vmin)*100 when the objective is to minimize.$n$nV is the value of the indicator for the RAS and the AAS.</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.tblIndic.startStandardization">Click on "calculate" to determine the level of performance of the rest of the indicators.</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.tblIndic.btn.standardize">Calculate</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.amoeba.title">GRAPHIC REPRESENTATION</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.amoeba.text">Once the indicators for the RAS and the AAS are standardized, we can visually represent them on a graph or a multiple criteria map. In this example, we selected the AMOEBA representation, on which we can easily identify the relative advantages of each management system. $n$nOn this graph, each indicator is graphed on a scale of 0 to 100, where 0 corresponds to the worse scenario possible for the given indicator, and 100, to the optimum. The colored areas represent the qualitative ranges assigned to each indicator. </msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.amoeba.SAR">RAS</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.amoeba.SAA">AAS</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.amoeba.notAllStandardized">Please, standardize ALL indicators first </msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.amoeba.details">The multiple criteria map AMOEBA (A general Method for Ecological and Biological Assessment), based on a radial graph, was originally designed to evaluate ecological systems (Ten Brink et al. 1991). Since then, the map has become popular for a diversity of integrated analysis. The method is flexible and can be adapted to different needs.$n$nTo construct the map, it is necessary to transform the indicator’s original measurement units into a common scale in order to use symmetrical axes. Each axis in the radial graph represents a standardized indicator. The AMOEBA shape is determined by the values of the system on each axis. A line is drawn from one point on an axis to the next forming a polygon. $n$nThe AMOEBA presented in this exercise integrates some modifications by Gomiero (2004), which include the use of qualitative domains and the zero away from the center. The domains or qualitative regions are very useful to clearly visualize the state of each indicator. The separation of the zero from the center allows the interpreter to distinguish the values close to or lower than zero. In addition, it avoids generating overly negative impressions about low values.</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.tradeOff.title">RELATIONS AMONG INDICATORS </msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.tradeOff.text1">It is a common misconception to think that sustainability indicators can be maximized simultaneously; that is, to think that it is possible to design a system that is the most productive, stable, adaptable, equitable and self-reliant, all at the same time. In reality, it is very difficult or even impossible to achieve this because, in general, when we try to improve on an attribute, we cause changes in other aspects of the system. </msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.tradeOff.text2">Some changes can be synergic, that is when one indicator positively affects another, or competing, that is when an indicator negatively affects another indicator. </msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.tradeOff.text3">The graph shown represents the RAS. Erosion in this system is quite high. An alternative solution is using crop residues as mulch to reduce soil loss.$n$nMaximize soil retention on the RAS. Move the bar to select the % cover you consider adequate.</msg>
<msg key="defineAmoebas.tradeOff.text4">What changes do you observe?$nWhich indicators are correlated?$nWhich indicators have relations of competition?$nWhich indicators have synergic relations?$nThink of a hypothesis about how indicators interact.</msg>

<!-- indicator table component -->
<msg key="tblIndicators.col1.title">Indicator</msg>
<msg key="tblIndicators.col2.title">Units</msg>
<msg key="tblIndicators.col3.title">Direction$nof change</msg>
<msg key="tblIndicators.col4.title">RAS</msg>
<msg key="tblIndicators.col5.title">AAS</msg>
<msg key="tblIndicators.col6.title">Vmin</msg>
<msg key="tblIndicators.col7.title">Vmax</msg>
<msg key="tblIndicators.col8.title">Std$nRAS</msg>
<msg key="tblIndicators.col9.title">Std$nAAS</msg>
<msg key="tblIndicators.col10.title">Standardize</msg>

<!-- optimizer component -->
<msg key="optimizer.intro.title">STANDARDIZATION</msg>
<msg key="optimizer.detailPane.title">Introduction</msg>
<msg key="optimizer.intro.text">Select the minimum and maximum values using your own judgment and the information given. You can drag the Min and Max points on the graph or type the data directly on the table. </msg>
<msg key="optimizer.graphic.title">GRAPH</msg>
<msg key="optimizer.livedata.levelSatisfaction">Level of performance</msg>
<msg key="optimizer.yAxis">Level of performance</msg>
<msg key="optimizer.xAxis">Return (ton/ha/year)</msg>
<msg key="optimizer.excellent">Very good</msg>
<msg key="optimizer.acceptable">Acceptable</msg>
<msg key="optimizer.deficient">Deficient</msg>
<msg key="optimizer.veryDeficient">Very deficient</msg>
<msg key="optimizer.graphic.text">The graph represents a function of the indicator’s level of performance (on a scale 0-100) and its real value, $n$n$n$n$nwhere NSji is the level of satisfaction for each management system (j) for each indicator (i), xji is the value of the indicator i for the management system j, and min xji and max xji are, respectively, the minimum and maximum values of the interval defined for each indicator (i); xji, min xji and max xji are expressed in the original units. In our example, we have multiplied NSji X 100, to express the level of satisfaction in percentages; however, any other scale can be used. $n$nThe minimum value can be defined according to critical values, any value lower than these render the system unsustainable or unacceptable for a certain group of social actors. The maximum value can represent average reference values or extremes for the locality or region studied (for example, maximum return obtained in a locality or period).$n$nNOTE: When the objective is to minimize, the interpretation of minimum and maximum is reversed, that is, the minimum represents our best scenario, while the maximum the worst. In such case, we should substitute (xji-min xji) for (max xji- xji).</msg>
<msg key="optimizer.qualitative.title">QUALITATIVE VALUES</msg>
<msg key="optimizer.qualitative.text">The colored areas refer to qualitative values assigned to ranges of quantitative values on the performance scale.$n$nThe ranges used in the example are 0-25 (Very deficient), 25-50 (Deficient), 50-75 (Acceptable), and 75-100 (Very good). If the value for a given indicator falls within the range 0-25, it requires our greatest attention. If, on the contrary, the value falls within the range 75-100 (green), then we can say that the system is doing well on that indicator.$n$nYou can define as many qualitative values as you find necessary. It is also possible to define ranges of a different size; for instance, we could define a wider range (e.g. 0-50) for values such as “very deficient” and narrower ranges (e.g. 90-100) for qualitative values such as “very good”. To keep it simple on this example, we have defined only four values with equal intervals for all indicators. $n$nMore examples can be found in Prescott (1997).</msg>


<!-- trade off component -->
<msg key="tradeOff.amoeba.originalSystem">Original System</msg>
<msg key="tradeOff.amoeba.modifiedSystem">Modified System</msg>
<msg key="tradeOff.slideBar.titleTxt">Cover percentage</msg>
<msg key="tradeOff.slideBar.desc">Drag the bar or insert the value directly</msg>
<msg key="tradeOff.slideBar.actualLevel">Percentage:</msg>

<!-- step 6: Conclusions -->
<msg key="conclusions.intro.title">STEP 6: CONCLUSIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS</msg>
<msg key="conclusions.intro.text">This step ends the first evaluation cycle. It is the point where we recapitulate the results of the analysis in order to make a value judgment and determine how the different management systems compare in terms of sustainability.$n$nIt is also the time to reflect on the evaluation process itself and to lay down the strategies and recommendations that will allow the next evaluation cycle to take place.$n$nConclusions and recommendations can revolve around the following points:$n$nPriority action and research areas to be explored in the following cycle.$n$nConclusions and recommendations regarding the methodology used.$n$nDesign of alternatives and decision-making processes to improve and innovate the management systems for the following evaluation cycle.</msg>

<!-- buttons -->
<msg key="btn.credits">Credits and Acknowledgements</msg>
<msg key="btn.principalMenu">Back to Steps Menu</msg>
<msg key="btn.enter">Enter</msg>
<msg key="btn.next">Next</msg>
<msg key="btn.previous">Previous</msg>
<msg key="btn.accept">Accept</msg>
<msg key="btn.cancel">Cancel</msg>
<msg key="btn.close">Close</msg>
<msg key="btn.add">Add</msg>
<msg key="btn.addAll">Add All</msg>
<msg key="btn.addSubsystem">Add Subsystem</msg>
<msg key="btn.addComponents">Add Components</msg>
<msg key="btn.addFlows">Add Flows</msg>
<msg key="btn.graphic">Graph</msg>
<msg key="btn.restartExcercise">Restart Exercise</msg>
<msg key="btn.qualitativeValues">Qualitative Values</msg>
<msg key="btn.exit">Back to Main Menu</msg>
<msg key="btn.gotoTopMenu">Back to Main Menu</msg>
<msg key="btn.exit">Back to Main Menu</msg>
<msg key="btn.principalMenu">Back to Steps Menu</msg>
<msg key="btn.gotoStep1">Go to Step 1</msg>
<msg key="btn.gotoStep2">Go to Step 2</msg>
<msg key="btn.gotoStep3And4">Go to Step 3 y 4</msg>
<msg key="btn.gotoStep5">Go to Step 5</msg>
<msg key="btn.gotoStep6">Go to Step 6</msg>
<msg key="btn.amoeba.seeMore">Read more about AMOEBA</msg>

<!-- general -->
<msg key="combo.select">-- Select --</msg>
<msg key="general.txtTitle">Step by Step</msg>
<msg key="general.txtSubtitle">FRAMEWORK FOR THE EVALUATION OF NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT SYSTEMS INCORPORATING SUSTAINABILITY INDICATORS </msg>

