<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<!-- initialization -->
<msg key="init.loadData">LOADING DATA...</msg>
<msg key="init.initializeGlobals">SEARCHING GLOBAL VARIABLES...</msg>
<msg key="init.initializeActivities">STARTING EXERCISES...</msg>
<msg key="init.title">SYSTEM DYNAMICS AND SUSTAINABILITY ATTRIBUTES</msg>
<msg key="init.skipIntro">Skip Intro ></msg>
<msg key="init.description1">Simulate the dynamics of a simple agro-ecosystem and learn about the systemic nature of</msg>
<msg key="init.description2">the sustainability attributes: Stability, Resilience, Reliability, and Adaptability</msg>
<msg key="init.authors">Luis Garcia-Barrios and Max Pimm</msg>
<msg key="init.support">Project made possible with the support of:</msg>
<msg key="init.support.1">Centro de Investigaciones en Ciencias Agropecuarias(CICA- UAEM)</msg>
<msg key="init.support.2">Centro de Investigaciones en Ecosistemas(CIEco-UNAM)</msg>
<msg key="init.support.3">Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnología (CONACYT)</msg>
<msg key="init.support.4">El Colegio de la Frontera Sur (ECOSUR)</msg>
<msg key="init.support.5">Grupo Interdisciplinario de Tecnología Rural Apropiada (GIRA A.C)</msg>
<msg key="init.support.6">Secretaría de Medio Ambiente y Recursos Naturales(SEMARNAT)</msg>
<!-- presentation -->
<msg key="presentation.title">INTRODUCTION</msg>
<msg key="presentation.mainText">
This program presents a simple story in which the behavior of a population of insects is crucial for the sustainability of a fruit production-and-gathering process that provides a major complement to the modest income of a community of small farmers. The behavior of this population of insects depends on its continuous interaction with other organisms (systemic behavior).$n$n A series of systemic population behaviors, and their effects on fruit production, will be seen during the course of this story. You will also be introduced to several concepts used in the MESMIS framework (through these behaviors), so that you will better understand their abstract definitions. (You can find these definitions in the upper right hand corner of the screen). In this way, you will understand the meaning of some attributes that, in general terms, will indicate whether or not a systemic process is capable of maintaining itself functioning adequately. (Click on the glossary icon –on the upper right corner– to read the definitions of the sustainability attributes).$n$n The situations described in this module are undoubtedly simplifications of reality. However, if you want to learn by playing and decide to accept the rules of the game, you will find this exercise useful in understanding the general meanings of these attributes. Hopefully, this game will become a basis for your study of these concepts and that you will be able to apply them to concrete situations.$n$n This module uses the “SUSSI” (Sustainability and Systemic) scenario simulation program. To play, you do not need to be familiar with or be able to perform any mathematical procedures. The program combines several dynamic models that describe changes in the species populations that result from its intra- and inter-specific interactions. The formulas and calculations are internally executed by the program. The rules and parameters of the interactions occurring within the system are defined quantitatively; however, you only need to understand them qualitatively. If you want more details on these models, you can contact Luis Garcia-Barrios.</msg>
<msg key="presentation.credits.title">Credits and Acknowledgements</msg>
<msg key="presentation.credits.txt">Luis Garcia-Barrios specialized in agricultural ecology and modeling. He is a researcher at ECOSUR, in Chiapas, Mexico. Luis is the author of the idea, script, and texts in this game. He created and parameterized the SUSSI model. He wrote a test version of this model using MS Excel. Luis also designed the graphics and illustrations, and collaborated with Max Pimm in the graphic design. You can contact Luis at lgarcia@sclc.ecosur.mx$n$nMax Pimm is a mathematician and independent programmer. He lives in Barcelona, Spain. Max created the computer version of these models. He also developed and programmed animations, graphics, and user interfaces. He directed and created the games graphic design. You can contact Max at mail@alwayssunny.com$n$nOmar Masera, Marta Astier, Yankuic Galvan, Tamara Ortiz, Carlos Gonzalez and Romeo Trujillo –also members of MESMIS Project– made valuable suggestions that helped develop this program. $n$nTranslation from Spanish: Jessica Fong, Gabriela Tobias and Diane Miyoshi.</msg>
<!-- Graph components -->
<msg key="graph.populationVsTime.xAxisLabel">Time (weeks)</msg>
<msg key="graph.populationVsTime.footNote">Blue dots mark the second week of June (when pollination must occur) through a period of 5 years.</msg>
<msg key="graph.populationVsTime.yAxisLabel">Number of individuals </msg>
<msg key="graph.populationVsTime.limit.polinization">Economic Threshold ={0} Individuals</msg>
<msg key="graph.populationVsTime.limit.epidemia.h1">Blue insects epidemic threshold={0}</msg>
<msg key="graph.h1PhaseDiagram.xAxisLabel">Number of individuals</msg>
<msg key="graph.h1PhaseDiagram.initCond">Initial Condition: {0}</msg>
<msg key="graph.populationVsTime.separatrix">Unstable Point of Equilibrium</msg>
<msg key="graph.h1PhaseDiagram.region.canPolinate">Population capable of adequate pollination</msg>
<msg key="graph.h1PhaseDiagram.region.canNotPolinate">Population incapable of$nadequate pollination</msg>
<msg key="graph.h1PhaseDiagram.birthDeathRate.birthLevel">Births</msg>
<msg key="graph.h1PhaseDiagram.birthDeathRate.deathLevel">Deaths</msg>

<!-- step titles -->
<msg key="popEvolution.step1.text">Introduction</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step2.text">Sustainable fruit gathering</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step3.text">A problem arises and is investigated</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step4.text">Production depends upon blue insects</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step5.text">Blue insect – Observation 1</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step6.text">Blue insect – Observation 2</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step7.text">Blue insect – Observation 3</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step8.text">Population in stable equilibrium </msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step9.text">Population numbers impede mating</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step10.text">Disturbances in the population</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step11.text">Disturbances in the population</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step12.text">Disturbances lead to another basin</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step13.text">Disturbances lead to another basin</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step14.text">Blue insect dynamics. Synthesis</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step15.text">Problem: Blue insects epidemic</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step16.text">The epidemic impedes adequate pollination</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step17.text"> The epidemic impedes adequate pollination</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step18.text">How can we solve this problem?</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step19.text"> How can we solve this problem?</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step20.text">A predator is introduced</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step21.text">A predator is introduced</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step22.text">The predator brings a new problem</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step23.text">The yellow insect invades</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step24.text">Mistery: The tree produces fruit</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step25.text">Solve the mistery</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step26.text">Conclusion</msg>
<msg key="popEvolution.step27.text">Corollary on systemic sustainability attributes</msg>

<!-- story texts -->
<msg key="story.animation.seeAnimation">See animation</msg>
<msg key="story.animation.playAll">Complete sequence</msg>
<msg key="story.startStory.title">SUSTAINABLE FRUIT GATHERING</msg>
<msg key="story.startStory.text">There is a village in the desert where farmer families complement their modest income by gathering wild fruits. The fruits grow on thorny bushes native to the region and are collected by women once a year. These fruits are highly demanded in organic markets.The village women commercialize them as partners of a fair-trade program where you provide technical assistance.$n$nBush density is very low (60 plants/ha). As a result, gathering the fruits requires walking over long distances under harsh conditions. The bushes thorns make the task even more difficult. Nonetheless, this has been a sustainable activity for many years since the abundant production of each bush compensates the effort involved in gathering.</msg>
<msg key="story.women.title">A PROBLEM ARISES AND IS INVESTIGATED</msg>
<msg key="story.women.text">A few years ago, production per bush declined to the point that it could no longer compensate the effort invested in gathering the fruits. Women abandoned gathering and their families quality of life deteriorated.$n$nThey discussed the problem with you, and you offered to help them put together a participative research effort.Together you would find the cause of the problem and offer solutions. The women organized into groups to observe the plants throughout the year, not just in the gathering season like they used to.</msg>
<msg key="story.blueInsect.title">PRODUCTION DEPENDS UPON INSECTS</msg>
<msg key="story.blueInsect.text">The women discovered blue insects living on the bushes. The insects are born on one bush and rarely migrate to a different one. Blue insects feed on tender leaves and pollinate the bush flowers. They are, therefore, essential to fruit production. Women also observed the flowering period is very short; flowers are receptive for only one week in mid-June. Since the insects prefer the upper part of the bush, fruits are most abundant here.$n$nThe research group also found that, when there are less than 2.5 insects per plant during the flowering period (150 insects/ha), pollination on the upper part of the bush is incomplete. Most of the bushes had fewer than 2 insects during the flowering period, which explained the decline in production.$n$nIn addition, they observed that the insect reproduces throughout the year. Also, the quantity of insects varies in time and from one bush to the next: some bushes have more insects than others, and some –during certain seasons– have none. The group does not understand how population fluctuates or why it declined when it is most needed for pollination.$n$nHowever, they do understand the sustainability of the system of production depends on the dynamics of the blue insect population.Therefore, they focus their attention on investigating its dynamics. They decide to observe the population in an area without pollination problems. So, they organize to monitor the bushes over one hectare and register insect births and deaths over one year.$n$nThey discovered the following...</msg>
<msg key="story.blueInsectGrowsToLimit.title">BLUE INSECT – OBSERVATION 1</msg>
<msg key="story.blueInsectGrowsToLimit.text">An initial population of over 74 insects/ha grows until the count reaches 550 individuals/ha (approximately 9 insects per bush).</msg>
<msg key="story.blueInsectDropsToLimit.title"> BLUE INSECT – OBSERVATION 2</msg>
<msg key="story.blueInsectDropsToLimit.text">If the population grows over 550, it declines back to this number.
</msg>
<msg key="story.blueInsectBelowAllee.title"> BLUE INSECT – OBSERVATION 3</msg>
<msg key="story.blueInsectBelowAllee.text">If it is initially less than 74 (less than 1.25 insects per bush), then the population tends to disappear.$n$nHow would you explain these three situations?$n$nWhat insect-to-plant or insect-to-insect interactions can cause such behaviors?$n$nWhen you have an answer, click “Next”</msg>
<msg key="story.pertubations.title">DISTURBANCES IN THE POPULATION</msg>
<msg key="story.pertubations.text">Until now, we have only examined changes in the population generated by its own internal interactions. However, there are also changes induced by EXTERNAL ELEMENTS; that is, ELEMENTS INFLUENCING A SYSTEM WITHOUT BEING INFLUENCED BY IT:$n$nThe group observed that in some bushes the population grew, declined momentarily, and then recovered.$n$nSome insects were accidentally blown away by the wind. Many dehydrated on the hot sand before climbing back onto the bush. Yet, only a few days afterwards the deceased insects were replaced by their descendants.$n$nThis kind of population change is not a product of disequilibrium in the system’s internal forces. Rather, they result from the action of external forces acting on the system, which are often unpredictable.
</msg>
<msg key="story.pertubationsBelowAllee.title">DISTURBANCES LEAD TO ANOTHER BASIN </msg>
<msg key="story.pertubationsBelowAllee.text">The group also observed a number of population declines due to wind were not followed by population recoveries but led to extinction.$n$nIn such cases, disturbances (e.g. a decline from 3 to 1 individual) led to insufficient mating and pushed the subsystem toward its left basin.</msg>
<msg key="story.disease.title">PROBLEM: BLUE INSECT EPIDEMIC</msg>
<msg key="story.disease.text">Later, the group began to study the situation in the affected area. They discovered the presence of a disease that kills the insect in less than a week.$n$nIn the first stage, the disease appears on a small number of bushes and affects few individuals. However, when the insect population reaches 240 individuals/ha (that is, 5 individuals per bush), overpopulation forces some insects to move to a different bush. And, by this process, the disease is rapidly disseminated throughout the area.$n$nA portion of the population is able to survive. Still, the population suddenly decreases to nearly the state of unstable equilibrium (74 individuals), which is far below the economic threshold of pollination. </msg>
<msg key="story.diseaseNoPolinization.title">THE EPIDEMIC IMPEDES ADEQUATE POLLINATION</msg>
<msg key="story.diseaseNoPolinization.text">Unfortunately, the epidemic causes the highest mortality only a few weeks before the bushes flowering period. Even though the population starts recovering immediately, the number of pollinators does not reach the economic limit on time.</msg>
<msg key="story.discussion1.title">HOW CAN WE SOLVE THIS PROBLEM?</msg>
<msg key="story.discussion1.text">The group discussed several alternatives to solve the problem.$n$nTogether, you came up with a list of possible technical and/or ecological interventions. What would you include on this list? Think about it, and click “Next” when you are ready. </msg>
<msg key="story.discussion2.title">HOW CAN WE SOLVE THIS PROBLEM?</msg>
<msg key="story.discussion2.text">The women discussed a series of alternatives and their respective disadvantages (shown in parenthesis) with you. Here are some of them:$n$nA. Eliminate the cause of the problem$n1. Attack the disease using a chemical bactericide (expensive and labor-consuming).$n2.Select bacteria-resistant insects (bacteria mutate rapidly and could overcome resistance in a very short time).$nB.Control the consequences of the problem:$n3.Prevent population numbers from reaching 300 when flowering season approaches. This would prevent epidemic and pollinator shortages. Population control could be achieved through:$n$na)Chemical control (costly and labor-consuming)$nb)Biological control (it would be necessary to identify a predator that could keep blue insect populations under 300, and above 75).$n$nThe women decided to reject options (1) and (3a) because fruit production must be certified organic. In addition, the use of chemical inputs would increase their dependence on products whose price and supply is outside their control; which, in turn, would reduce their capacity for SELF-RELIANCE in solving the problem.$n$nThey concluded option (2) would be effective but temporary. Finally, they agreed to explore option (3b), biological control, because it would be inexpensive and they would continue to be self-reliant.$n$nA few months later they managed to get breeding stock of carnivorous insect that feeds on the blue insect. They released the carnivores and started monitoring both populations of insects.</msg>
<msg key="story.carnivore.title">A PREDATOR IS INTRODUCED</msg>
<msg key="story.carnivore.text">Fortunately, the predator established well in the area during the first year and it successfully reduced the population of blue insects to a level that prevented epidemics without impeding pollination.$n$nThe group discovered the predator also has an ecology. A population of fewer than 10 individuals/ha makes it difficult to for them to find a mate and population diminishes to zero. They also suffer epidemics, which reduce populations of more than 60 individuals/ha.  </msg>
<msg key="story.biologicalSolutionFails.title">THE PREDATOR BRINGS A NEW PROBLEM</msg>
<msg key="story.biologicalSolutionFails.text">The women of the village were very pleased during the next two years. The population of blue insects behaved similarly to what SUSSI had predicted.$n$nBut, on the third year, fruit production declined again.$n$nSeveral women were disappointed and abandoned the group. Others were interested in finding out what went wrong to look for a new solution.$n$nThey monitored the bushes for yet another year and discovered this:$n$nBlue and carnivore insects, and their respective pathogens, were still present on the bushes. However, a third insect species had established itself on the upper part of the bush.$n$nThe newcomer, a yellow insect, also feeds on tender leaves, but shows no interest in pollinating the bush flowers.$n$nIn addition, the women found the yellow insect is winning the competition for food and is displacing the blue insect. The carnivore also feeds on yellow insects, which also have a lower mating threshold (66) and an upper epidemic threshold (240).</msg>
<msg key="story.solvedByItself.title">MISTERY: THE TREE PRODUCES FRUIT</msg>
<msg key="story.solvedByItself.text">Last year, to everyone’s surprise, fruit production recovered. This time, most of the fruits appeared on the lower part of the bush. The women were intrigued. They wanted to know if fruition was circumstantial or if there was some change that could make gathering sustainable again. So, they invite you to a meeting.$n$nOn your way to the village, you decide to explore the problem using SUSSI. Your turn on your laptop and study a variety of changes in the agro-ecosystem’s web of interactions that could explain what the women had told you. To begin, you hypothesize there was a change in the behavior of one of the three kinds of insects. You come up with several possibilities and analyze the impact of each one on competition and predation relationships among the blue, yellow, and carnivore insects. To carry out this exercise, click “Next”.</msg>
<msg key="story.conclusion.title">CONCLUSION OF THE STORY</msg>
<msg key="story.conclusion.text">You arrive at the village, meet with the women, and present your results. You offer the following explanations:$n$n1) Blue insects appear to have migrated to the lower part of the bush, and now the three species of insects can coexist.$n$n2) The phenomenon observed this year does not seem to be circumstantial. Rather, it suggests the pollinator has adapted to the new structure of the agro-ecosystem and, abundant fruit production on the lower part of the bush could be a stable, resilient, and reliable process.$n$nThe results encouraged the women to verify the new scenario through monitoring. They also decide to reorganize and resume gathering and selling the fruits in the following years.</msg>
<msg key="story.corrollary.title">COROLLARY: SUSTAINABILITY AND SYSTEMS</msg>
<msg key="story.corrollary.text">The natural “blue insect-bush” system was able to sustain itself in such a way as to be confident that the insect population was sufficient for the economic sustainability of fruit production. Such SYSTEMIC functioning was STABLE, RESILIENT, and RELIABLE in the face of moderate external forces that DISTURBED the system.$n$nHowever, the agro-ecosystem experienced several structural changes. New groups of organisms entered the system and affected the dynamics of the blue insect. The arrival of the blue insect pathogen was natural. On the other hand, the carnivore and yellow insects were introduced directly or indirectly by the women as they intervened to control the pathogen. Apparently, the new system was heading towards the extinction of the pollinator, the abandonment of production, and even the local extinction of the bush (seed production was also declining). Nonetheless, the system continued to restructure and reorganize itself until it recovered a way of functioning that was favorable to the coexistence of bushes, insects, and humans.$n$nWomen demonstrated their ABILITY TO ADAPT and their SELF-RELIANCE (SELF-EMPOWERMENT) by (1) acquiring the knowledge necessary to understand the behavior of the system, and (2) actively seeking solutions that were under their own economic control. Initially, their strategy of biological control failed because it had unexpected direct and indirect effects. Ultimately, however, it induced the blue insect to ADAPT to a new structure in the resulting system which functions differently. Even so, it recovered stability, resulting in the sustainable production of the fruits (in the predictable future), and in wellbeing for gatherers.$n$n--  THE END  --$n$n</msg>
<!-- model texts -->
<msg key="model.blueInsectTendsToNaturalLimit.title">POPULATION IN STABLE EQUILIBRIUM</msg>
<msg key="model.blueInsectTendsToNaturalLimit.text">Why is population attracted to the value of 550/ha?$n$nInsects compete against each other for the foliage they feed on. When insect count increases, competition causes individual females to reproduce in decreasing numbers. Even though the total number of new insects per week increases as does the total number of individuals, birth rate actually decreases (due to competition) and so does the population growth rate. On the other hand, mortality per individual per week is constant, because (in this case) it does not depend upon population density. As a result, total mortality per week is always directly proportional to the number of insects.$n$nIn systemic terms, this means the population of blue insects interacts with itself. There is POSITIVE FEEDBACK in direct relations such as “the more the mothers, the more the offspring”. But, there is also NEGATIVE FEEDBACK in inverse relations such as: “the more the mothers, the fewer the offspring per mother”.$n$nFor each population size a specific number of insects hatch and die during a given week. For populations ranging from 74 to 539 individuals, births outnumber deaths causing the population to grow. Because these opposing forces are of different magnitude, population behaves as a subsystem in DISEQUILIBRIUM, in which all population sizes are TRANSITORY STATES that will lead to a different state in the following week. When the population is 550, the birth and death processes find EQUILIBRIUM, and the population reaches a STATIONARY DYNAMIC STATE. For populations greater than 550, total deaths per week outnumber births. The system is in disequilibrium and population decreases until it reaches 550 again.$n$nThe disequilibrium and equilibrium of the processes that “run” the subsystem can be illustrated using the “rail-and-marble” tool shown on the graph above. Use your computer mouse to pick up the marble and release it on a population value “X” between 76 and 539. Observe how the disequilibrium forces move the ball across different values of X until it reaches 550. The graph on the right represents the same phenomenon, expressed as X against time. Pick up the marble again and place it on a value greater than 550. Observe what happens in the two graphs.$n$nIn systemic terms, the stationary state of 550 is a state of equilibrium that acts as an ATTRACTOR for all other population states described. These other states that are attracted towards 550 form the stationary state BASIN OF ATTRACTION. 550 is a STATE OF STABLE EQUILIBRIUM, since population outside this state tends to return to it. This is due to the subsystem’s INTERNAL PROCESSES OF SELF-REGULATION. On the graph above, the basin is the whole rail, and the state of stable equilibrium is its lower point. When the rail is U-shaped, we say the subsystem has a range of population values within which it is STABLE.$n$nClick “Next”.</msg>
<msg key="model.blueInsectExtinguishBelowAllee.title">POPULATION IN UNSTABLE EQUILIBRIUM</msg>
<msg key="model.blueInsectExtinguishBelowAllee.text">Why are populations lower than 74/ha attracted towards zero?$n$nWhen there are fewer insects, there is more food available per insect, and thus, each individual produces more offspring. This, however, has a limit. Because insects tend to remain on the same bush, when the population is reduced to a certain density, the probability of finding a mate is also much reduced. When the average number of individuals per bush is less than 1.25 (that is 74/ha), there are also fewer offspring than deaths, and the population tends to decrease. When X reaches zero, births and deaths find equilibrium, because, obviously, neither can occur.$n$nUnder these conditions, the rail takes a different form. Pick up the marble and place it on a value of X lower than 74. Which direction did it move? Where did it stop?  Try to place the marble on X=74. What happened?$n$nOn X=74, births and deaths are in equilibrium; hence, the system is in a stationary state. Yet, if population moves even slightly from this state, population will be attracted to zero, or 550, depending on the direction of the given change. X=74 is a STATE OF UNSTABLE EQUILIBRIUM. It is a state that REPELS all neighboring states and, therefore, it DOES NOT HAVE A BASIN OF ATTRACTION.$n$nThis means that, in fact, the subsystem has two basins of attraction, each one having its own state of stable equilibrium (zero and 550). They are divided by the state of unstable equilibrium X=74. If the subsystem is on the right basin, it tends to stay on a value that allows for complete pollination and fruition. Contrarily, if the subsystem is on the left basin, it is a certainty that fruit gathering will not be profitable.$n$nClick “Change scale” to have a better view of the left basin (note the X axis scale is 1 to 100). </msg>
<msg key="model.pertubations.title">DISTURBANCES IN THE POPULATION</msg>
<msg key="model.pertubations.text">Any change caused by an external force is called a DISTURBANCE. Its magnitude depends on the INTENSITY OF THE EXTERNAL FORCE and the RESISTANCE, or opposing force, exerted by the subsystem.$n$nObserve the graphs: if the disturbance does not move the population outside the basin where it is found, then the population tends to return to its previous state. The rate at which it returns to its previous state is called RESILIENCE, which depends on how fast the subsystem’s positive and/or negative feedback processes occur.
</msg>
<msg key="model.pertubationsBelowAllee.title">DISTURBANCES LEAD TO ANOTHER BASIN</msg>
<msg key="model.pertubationsBelowAllee.text">Place the marble on X=80. Observe the disturbances and pay attention to which basin the marble ends up in. Repeat this action several times.$n$nWhen the disturbance occurs at a population size close to 80, it is pushed below 74. The marble crosses the lower limit of the right basin and rolls to the left basin stable equilibrium (X=0).$n$nThe system’s RELIABILITY of keeping the population in a given basin depends on (1) the frequency and intensity of disturbances, and (2) the amplitude of the basin.$n$nFor instance, if insects were less able to find a mate and wind was more intense, the left basin would be wider and the probability that the population is pushed toward it would increase as well. And so, the reliability of the right basin would decrease.</msg>
<msg key="model.firstConclusions.title">BLUE INSECT DYNAMICS: A SYNTHESIS</msg>
<msg key="model.firstConclusions.text">In short, the group discovered that, in the area without problems in fruit production, production depends on the population dynamics of the blue insect. There is a lower economic limit for this population (150 individuals/ha) below which pollination is insufficient to make gathering profitable. About the insect’s population dynamics, they learned:$n$n1) Population tends to grow and rapidly exceed this limit, since it is attracted toward the state of stable equilibrium 550$n$n2)There is a lower ecological limit (74 individuals/ha), below which population decreases to the state of stable equilibrium zero.$n$n3)Disturbances caused by external forces present randomly on the population. If disturbances do not cause the population to reach the ecologic inferior limit of the right basin, population recovers and there are no economic consequences unless a disturbance coincides with the flowering season.
</msg>
<msg key="model.disease.title">THE EPIDEMIC IMPEDES ADEQUATE POLLINATION</msg>
<msg key="model.disease.text">The group built a model to predict future scenarios using SUSSI. On the simulator graph, they could see that the process would repeat every year, generating sawtooth-shaped oscillations. If a disturbance occurs when the population is low, the system could shift to the left basin and population would tend toward zero. In any case, pollination would be inadequate.</msg>
<msg key="model.carnivore.title">A PREDATOR IS INTRODUCED</msg>
<msg key="model.carnivore.text">The group built a new scenario simulation model using SUSSI, now including the influence of the predator.$n$nThe graph to the right shows the simulation of each species dynamics over a period of 5 years. Repeat the process several times by clicking “Generate”.$n$nThese dynamics are the result of a web of intra- and inter-specific interactions present in the agro-ecosystem (graphed above). (Read the relationships represented by the arrows by placing the cursor over them). Occasional disturbances do not significantly modify the dynamics or impede adequate pollination.
 </msg>
<msg key="model.h2.title"> THE YELLOW INSECT INVASION</msg>
<msg key="model.h2.text">The group used SUSSI to predict the system’s behavior under the invasion of the yellow insect. Activate the yellow insect and observe (on the graph to the right) a simulation of 5 years of the dynamics of each insect. These dynamics result from the extended web of intra- and inter-specific interactions (upper graph).$n$n  The women understood that the recent blue insect epidemic had a consequence that took time to become evident and could not be avoided by when the carnivore was present: when blue insects were reduced below its epidemic threshold (240 individuals/ha), enough tender foliage was left over to allow successful invasion of the yellow insect, which not only ate the surplus, but also competed strongly against the blue insect.$n$n  During the past three years, there was no harvest, and the group stopped meeting. You visit them only occasionally. At the beginning, the group thought of possible solutions. But, they had to rule out chemical control. They understood that a biological agent would have to be reintroduced over and over again, which seemed too complicated. The group dissolved and you visit them rarely.</msg>
<msg key="model.excercise.title">SOLVE THE MISTERY</msg>
<msg key="model.excercise.text">The table on the upper right corner of the screen shows the four types of interactions you will explore. Interactions are all selected on the central column. This column represents the intensity values of the interactions before the system’s recent change.$n$nIf you select a position on the right column, the intensity doubles. If you select a position on the left column, the intensity is reduced to half. The orange arrows on the diagram above will reflect any changes you make on the table.$n$nFirst, think of a hypothesis about the change that occurred. Then, modify the intensities according to your hypothesis. Finally, observe the graph to the right to see if the populations behaviors match the women’s report.$n$nQuestions:$n$nWhat change in the interactions can explain this observations over the years?$n$nAre these changes circumstantial and ephemeral? Or, are they part of a pattern of re-establishing sustainability of the production system?</msg>
<msg key="model.excercise.clue">Have you considered this scenario?$n$nUntil now, all three insects have preferred the upper part of the bush. Both the yellow and the predatory insects were exerting ecological pressure on the blue insect. This pressure could have forced a change in the behavior of the blue insect and induced it to explore the lower part of the bush.$n$n  It is also possible that a blue insect phenotype predisposed to inhabit the lower part of the bush already existed in this population and, after a few generations, natural selection made it the population dominant phenotype. The yellow and predator insects continued to live in the upper part of the bush.$n$n The blue insect’s migration should have changed the intensity of the four interactions. Reflect on these changes and test your ideas.</msg>
<msg key="model.excercise.answer">The migration of the blue insect changed the intensity of all four interactions. The effect of competition between the blue and yellow insects decreased. The effect of the predator on blue insects declined, while predation on yellow insects increased.$n$nUnder these new conditions, the three insect species can coexist. It is also expected that the blue insect population will be greater than 150 when pollination takes place. The normal disturbances in the system are not a threat to this process.$n$nAlmost all the web of interactions influences the system’s current behavior. The predator is controlled by food availability (blue and yellow insects populations) and its own frequent epidemics. The blue and yellow insects are controlled by intra- and inter-specific competition and predation.$n$nClick “See graph” to view the simulation graph.</msg>

<!-- relation table -->
<msg key="relationTable.col1_title">Interaction</msg>
<msg key="relationTable.h1h2_title">Blue competes against yellow</msg>
<msg key="relationTable.h2h1_title">Yellow competes against blue</msg>
<msg key="relationTable.ch1_title">Carnivore eats blue</msg>
<msg key="relationTable.ch2_title">Carnivore eats yellow</msg>

<!-- relation diagram -->
<msg key="relationDiag.r_h1_tree_1.description">Blue pollinates flowers (direct relation).</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_h1_tree_2.description">Blue eats leaves (inverse relation)</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_tree_h1.description">Leaves feed blue (direct relation)</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_h1_intra.description">Inverse and direct effects of blue population on its own growth</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_h1_c.description">Blue feeds carnivore (direct relation)</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_bacteria_h1.description">Bacteria kills blue (inverse relation)</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_c_h1.description">Carnivore eats blue (inverse relation)</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_h2_c.description">Yellow feeds carnivore (direct relation)</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_bacteria_c.description">Bacteria kills carnivore (inverse relation)</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_c_intra.description">Inverse and direct effects of carnivore population on its own growth
</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_c_h2.description">Carnivore eats yellow (inverse relation)</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_h1_h2.description">Blue takes food (leaves) away from yellow (inverse relation)</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_h2_h1.description">Yellow takes food away from blue (inverse relation)</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_h2_tree.description">Yellow eats leaves (inverse relations)</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_bacteria_h2.description">Bacteria kills yellow (inverse relation)</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_tree_h2.description">Leaves feed yellow (direct relation)</msg>
<msg key="relationDiag.r_h2_intra.description">Inverse and direct effects of yellow population on its own growth
</msg>

<!-- buttons -->
<msg key="btn.credits">Credits and Acknowledgements</msg>
<msg key="btn.generate">Generate</msg>
<msg key="btn.previous">Previous</msg>
<msg key="btn.next">Next</msg>
<msg key="btn.animate">Animate</msg>
<msg key="btn.gotoStart">Back to start</msg>
<msg key="btn.openGlosari">See glosary</msg>
<msg key="btn.gotoTopMenu">Back to main menu</msg>
<msg key="btn.seeSolution">See solution</msg>
<msg key="btn.seeSolutionNow">See solution NOW</msg>
<msg key="btn.continueTrying">Keep trying</msg>
<msg key="btn.seeGraph">See graph</msg>
<msg key="btn.changeScale">Change scale</msg>
<msg key="btn.enter">Enter</msg>
<msg key="btn.exit">Back to main menu</msg>
<msg key="btn.start">Start</msg>

<!-- general -->
<msg key="general.txtTitle">Design of Sustainable Systems of Production</msg>
<msg key="general.txtSubtitle"> FRAMEWORK FOR THE EVALUATION OF NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT SYSTEMS INCORPORATING SUSTAINABILITY INDICATORS</msg>
<msg key="general.glosario.content">A productive natural resource management system is sustainable when it is capable of maintaining itself over a reasonable period of time, and if it can change (when conditions require) to keep functioning in the long run. For this to occur, the ecological and social processes and resources that enable the system to function must be capable of reproducing themselves. This implies that these processes be self-promoting, self-regulating, and coordinated for compatibility. They must be able to buffer occasional adverse disturbances opportunely, and reorganize and adapt themselves when internal and external structural changes take place. This capacity to sustain itself through time (that is, to function by constantly changing) can be described in a general and schematic manner using seven systemic attributes (Masera et al., 1999). The definitions (updated by Luis Garcia-Barrios and Omar Masera-Cerutti for this game) are presented here:$n$nProductivity: The ratio of goods and services (products, revenues, environmental services, etc.) provided by the system per unit of time and unit of invested input.$n$nStability: A productive system is stable when it has internal mechanisms regulating the state of its critical variables, keeping them within a range of value that allows the system to function. Suppose an internal variable essential to the functioning of the system (e.g. productivity) is modified by an external disturbance. The change in productivity affects other system variables with which it interacts. If these interactions cause productivity to return to its original state, the system is “stable”. If, on the other hand, a change in productivity leads to processes that take the system further away from its original condition, then the system is “unstable”. A stable system internally buffers external disturbances; an unstable system amplifies them.$n$nResilience*: Only stable systems are resilient. Resilience refers to the rate at which a disturbed variable returns to its previous state. This rate can change during the process that leads the variable back to its original condition. For this reason, resilience can be evaluated at different intervals of the process, or as the average rate of the entire process. The faster the system returns, the more efficient are its mechanisms of self-regulation.$n$nReliability*: Disturbances can affect a critical variable to such a degree that the system’s mechanisms of self-regulation cannot revert the effects. This state is outside the system’s regulation/tolerance limits. A critical variable is reliable if it is unlikely to exceed the system’s tolerance limits. This probability increases and reliability decreases if (1) the frequency of disturbance increases, (2) the variables resistance to disturbances decreases, and (3) the range of values within which change is reversible narrows. Only stable systems are reliable. Unstable systems lack self-regulation or a range of tolerance. In these systems, the slightest disturbance tends to amplify the effects, instead of reverting. Unstable systems have zero reliance.$n$nAdaptability (or flexibility): a system of production is adaptable when it is able to reorganize internally to continue functioning in spite of irreversible internal or external changes. Most stable systems are adaptable only within certain limits. When one or more critical variables exceed the tolerance limits, an adaptable system can reorganize itself (adapt) to generate a new stable behavior and function under the new conditions. Systems lacking the ability to adapt end up disorganized, stop functioning and is destroyed.$n$nSelf-reliance: A system is more self-reliant when its ability to function, regulate itself, and evolve favorably depend more on its own internal resources, interactions and processes, and less on external conditions, disturbances, and interventions outside its control.$n$nEquity: A system of production is equitable when the costs and benefits are fairly distributed amongst the social agents involved (intra- and inter-generations). Equity not only has undeniable ethical value. It is a mechanism of social self-regulation and stability that contributes to the persistence and correct evolution of cooperation among the social agents that participate in the system.$n$n*Note: Some authors ( e.g. Berkes and Folke (eds), 2000) use the term “resilience” more broadly. For them, a system is more resilient when it is stable and highly reliable. For purposes of our methodology, we prefer to keep the concept resilience separate from reliability in order to analyze its components more easily.$n
</msg>
<msg key="general.glosario.title">GLOSSARY OF SUSTAINABILITY ATTRIBUTES</msg>


